<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Olivia B. Newton, Ph.D.</title>
        <description>My website</description>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:43:32 -0600</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:43:32 -0600</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.4.1</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Next-Generation Ecosystems for Scientific Computing: Harnessing Community, Software, and AI for Mission-Driven Team Science</title>
                <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;my-role&quot;&gt;My Role&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I serve as PI at the University of Montana. My collaborators are Lois Curfman McInnes at Argonne National Laboratory and Denice Ward Hood at the University of Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/Next-Gen/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/Next-Gen/</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Psychological Fidelity: A Systematic Review to Support Simulation-Based Training</title>
                <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;my-role&quot;&gt;My Role&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m co-leading this project with my undergraduate mentee, Andy Silva, at the University of Central Florida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychological fidelity is the degree that a simulation produces affective and cognitive processes that correspond to the real-world environment. The concept&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has been identified as an essential aspect of training efficacy and may be uniquely important for team training.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Notably, psychological fidelity has been associated with credibility, suspension of disbelief, and engagement in simulation-based training (SBT).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The concept of psychological fidelity in SBT was first introduced at least three decades ago but remains underutilized in the development and evaluation of simulation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;approach&quot;&gt;Approach&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Systematic literature review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preliminary-findings&quot;&gt;Preliminary Findings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out our HFES 2024 poster:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/psych_fid_HFESposter.png&quot; alt=&quot;Silva &amp;amp; Newton poster for HFES 2024.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/Psych-Fid/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/Psych-Fid/</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Expertise Utilization in Hybrid Teams</title>
                <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;my-role&quot;&gt;My Role&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.umt.edu/business-faculty-staff/directory/management-marketing.php?ID=8747&quot;&gt;Tyler R. Talbot&lt;/a&gt; to analyze findings from a lab study examining differences in performance and process associated with work configuration (face-to-face, remote, hybrid).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;status&quot;&gt;Status&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is in the analysis stage with the goal of submitting to a journal venue in the organizational sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/Hybrid-Teams/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/Hybrid-Teams/</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Team Learning for Better Scientific Software</title>
                <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;my-role&quot;&gt;My Role&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m leading this project with a group of 11 collaborators from universities and national laboratories across the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;workshop&quot;&gt;Workshop&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://tl4bssw.github.io/&quot;&gt;tl4bssw.github.io&lt;/a&gt; to learn about the workshop I organized in November 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acknowledgement: This work was supported by the Better Scientific Software Fellowship Program, a collaborative effort of the U.S. Department of Energy (DOE), Office of Advanced Scientific Research via ANL under Contract DE-AC02-06CH11357 and the National Nuclear Security Administration Advanced Simulation and Computing Program via LLNL under Contract DE-AC52-07NA27344; and by the National Science Foundation (NSF) via SHI under Grant No. 2327079.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/TL4BSSw/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/TL4BSSw/</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>